<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preservative for our money; or A way proposed, whereby some money may be kept in England which otherwise will all be gone or How we may carry on the war against France with vigour, and with much better effect than hitherto, and yet keep our money. By E.L.</title>
            <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2580A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826018</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30410</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1797:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preservative for our money; or A way proposed, whereby some money may be kept in England which otherwise will all be gone or How we may carry on the war against France with vigour, and with much better effect than hitherto, and yet keep our money. By E.L.</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by B. Motte, and are to be sold by E. Whitlock near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.L. = Edward Littleton.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed; page 2, a blank, not photographed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Finance, Public --  Great Britain --  1688-1815.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30410:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PRESERVATIVE For Our MONEY; OR A Way propoſed, whereby ſome MONEY may be kept in <hi>ENGLAND</hi> which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will all be gone: OR How we may carry on the War againſt <hi>France</hi> with Vigour, and with much better Effect than hitherto, and yet keep Our MONEY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Motte,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>E. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30410:2"/>
            <head>A PRESERVATIVE For our MONEY, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>OUR Money is running away by Millions, year after year: which will ſoon bring us, if it be not done already, to Beggery and Ruin. And now all the Talk is, of Mending our Money. As if a Man had almoſt bled to death, and were ſtill bleeding; and He, obſerving his Blood to be bad, ſhould be conſulting and contriving how to Mend his Blood. whereas his firſt Care ſhould be, how to ſtop his Bleeding. I confeſs our Money is not ſo good as it ſhould be: or rather, 'tis as bad as it can be. But yet, upon the whole matter, we ſhould think how to keep it, before we think how to mend it. For as things now go, whether it be mended or not mended, it will be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all away.</p>
            <p>It is now evident to all Men (but ſome Men ſaw it long ſince), that our great Payments abroad, and chiefly thoſe in <hi>Flanders,</hi> are the main Cauſe of the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Money. It therefore highly concerns us to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30410:3"/>put a ſtop to thoſe Payments at any rate. For we can bear them no longer: We have loſt ſo much Bloud already, that 'tis death to loſe more. But ſhall we not aſſiſt our Confederates? Yes, by all means, to the utmoſt of our power. For otherwiſe all <hi>Europe</hi> muſt be inſlaved to the <hi>French,</hi> and We among the reſt. It is therefore abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary that we keep our Money: and 'tis as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that we powerfully aſſiſt our Confederates. Both which things (tho ſeeming ſo inconſiſtent) may at once be done, by our Aſſailing the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt by Sea: or in other words, by a vigorous Deſcent upon <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Project of ſuch a Deſcent</hi> I preſumed to publiſh, in the year Ninety one. which Project was generally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, that the whole Kingdom was in Expectation that it would be proſecuted. Alſo the year next after, a Deſcent was intended: and another the year following. tho, as it fell out, thoſe Deſigns were not put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And in the third year was our Attempt at <hi>Cama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> Bay.</p>
            <p>But as to the Project, it is briefly this. That a good Body of Foot (twenty thouſand at leaſt, but the more the better) be Shipp'd for the Coaſt of <hi>France;</hi> there to move to and fro as they ſee occaſion, and to Land where they find it convenient: and further to ſeize and fortify ſome open Sea-Town, ſo as it may contain a great and ſtrong Garriſon. Which Garriſon being put in a State of defence, the Naval Army to proceed to new Adventures, and to ſeize and fortify other Places in like manner.</p>
            <p>Here I am to make good the two things before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd: Firſt, that in ſo doing we ſhall keep our Money; and ſecondly, that we ſhall effectually aſſiſt our Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates. To which two things I ſhall add a third; That the Deſign is very feaſable, and hardly poſſible to miſcarry.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30410:4"/>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, while we aſſail the Sea-Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> and plant Garriſons upon it; tho it be a great Expence, we ſhall ſtill keep our Money amongſt our ſelves. For whither ſhould it go? The <hi>French</hi> have good luck, if they get any thing from us in this Affair. And none elſe have to do with it. At preſent our Army in <hi>Flanders</hi> carries our Money thither, (ſome ſay a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and a half yearly); and our Fleet kept upon the Coaſts of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſtops Money from coming to us from thence: and a great Sum goes yearly to <hi>Piemont.</hi> But by a Deſcent upon <hi>France</hi> our Money will be no way diminiſh'd: and what ever is laid out, will come back and Circulate amongſt us. Here will be no carrying out our Coin and Bullion, nor the horrible diſadvantage of Remittances.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, By a Deſcend upon <hi>France</hi> we ſhall give moſt effectual Aſſiſtance to our Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. If we did nothing elſe, but overlay the <hi>French</hi> at Sea, and thereby deſtroy their Trade and Navigation; even this thing only would be an effectual Aſſiſtance. For whereas now the <hi>French</hi> are rampant, by the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Riches</hi> ('tis their Gazettiers word) which they have taken from us; they would then be impoveriſh'd to ſuch a Degree, as to be no way able to carry on the War againſt the Confederates. And this thing we muſt do in the firſt place. For we are ruin'd unleſs we powerfully protect our Trade; and the ſame Force that protects the Trade of <hi>England</hi> powerfully, will deſtroy that of <hi>France.</hi> Which things I hope our Parliament hath done already, by giving a larger Summe than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly for our Sea-Service. I have ſaid before, that our overlaying our Enemies by Sea, will prove a great Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to our Friends. But if beſide this, we alſo Aſſail the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt with Land-Forces, that Aſſiſtance will be much greater. For it will make ſo great a Diverſion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30410:5"/>taht both <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Piemont</hi> and <hi>Catalonia,</hi> will feel an exceeding great Eaſe and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by it. We are not able to maintain an Army in <hi>France:</hi> it will bring ſwift Deſtruction upon us. But we are able to maintain a Coaſt Warre. And our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates muſt and will be content, if we do for them as much as we are able. Suppoſe we take forty thouſand Men out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> to aſſail the <hi>French</hi> Coaſts. If theſe draw away, or keep back, a great number of <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> as they will certainly do; 'tis the ſame thing or better. And we may be making Deſcents in <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Bretagne,</hi> before the Armies in <hi>Flanders</hi> can take the field. By theſe Deſcents we ſhall touch the Enemy in his moſt ſenſible part, (as His Majeſty hath been pleas'd to expreſs it); that is, on his Sea Coaſt. How tender they are here, we found at our Bombarding of <hi>Havre de Grace.</hi> When we came before that Town, their Militia's and Regular Troops were commanded thither from all Quarters, with all haſte poſſible: and the Alarm reach'd <hi>Paris</hi> it ſelf. From whence that King (as all our Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions agreed) ſent away his own Guards to the Sea Coaſts. What to do? Not to hinder our Bombardment, for therein they could do no ſervice: but to hinder the Deſcent of our Land-Forces; who were not above ſeven thouſand in number. It was this handful of Men, that caus'd all that Terror and Affrightment. We may ſee therefore, that tho the Project here offer'd ſhould fail in the main; though we ſhould not be able to fortify and make good any Town, nor ſo much as Land our Men; yet the very Attempting theſe things in ſeveral places (in one place to day, and a hundred Miles off to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row); would ſo haraſs and torment the <hi>French,</hi> that they would never be able to bear it. But there is no fear that the Project here offer'd ſhould fail in the main, or not have its full Effect.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:30410:6"/>
            <p>In the third place, the thing propoſed is feaſable and eaſy, and hardly poſſible to miſcarry. 'Tis hardly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould hinder our Landing; 'tis hardly poſſible they ſhould hinder our Fortifying; or ſhould take from us the Places we fortify. I ſhall ſpeak firſt to our Landing. And here I muſt confeſs, that if we ſhould reſolve to Land at one place preciſely; and the <hi>French</hi> ſhould diſcover our Deſign ſome Months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand; and ſhould accordingly provide for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that place, with a great Body of Horſe and Foot, with Forts and Intrenchments, and with Bombs and Cannon; and we knowing all this, ſhould attempt that place notwithſtanding; we might fairly be repuls'd and baffled, as we were at <hi>Camaret</hi> Bay. But if we are at large, to Land where we ſee convenient, there is no ſuch danger. When we ſail'd from that Bay towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> along by the <hi>French</hi> Shores, the whole Country was in a high Alarm: and they brought down all their Forces to Guard their Coaſt. But yet, (as I have it from thoſe who ſaw it with their Eyes), there were a great many places, convenient for Landing, that had no Guard at all, either upon them or near them: we ſeeing far and wide that the Coaſt was clear. And both our Landmen and Seamen were moſt chearfully deſirous to go upon <hi>French</hi> Ground, if there had been Orders for it. Nor had they in truth found any Oppoſition. Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> doth fully demonſtrate, that the Landing upon an Enemies Coaſt can by no means be hindred. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Aſſailants be Maſters at Sea, and in caſe the Coaſt be large and acceſſible. Which thing is alſo confirm'd by the Experience of all Ages. For 'tis hardly to be found in Hiſtory, that ever any Attempt of this kind miſcarried, except Ours which I mention'd but now. And Reaſon tells us, that our Landing upon <hi>France</hi> (to ſpeak of that in particular) cannot be prevented. Suppoſe we have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30410:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>forty thouſand Men imbark'd, to aſſail the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt: and the <hi>French</hi> have fifty thouſand to defend it. Their Coaſt upon Our Channel, (for That muſt be the Scene of theſe Actions) is five hundred Miles in length. ſo that here is a thouſand Men for every ten Miles. But how ſlender a Guard will this be againſt our Invading Army? Had they a hundred thouſand Men, or a thouſand for every five Miles of ground, all would be found too few to oppoſe our Landing.</p>
            <p>I hope I have made out, that our Landing cannot be hinder'd by the <hi>French.</hi> I muſt now ſhew that they cannot hinder our Fortifying. It would be very ſtrange, if ſuch a Body of Men, having the Sea and a Fleet behind them; and having at leaſt ten days time to Intrench, before a ſuperiour or even an equal Force can be brought againſt them; ſhould not be able ſo to cover themſelves, as not to fear the Inſults of any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. The Works we caſt up at <hi>Landen</hi> in one ſhort night, the <hi>French</hi> Lines in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and ſeveral late Circumvallations, ſhew what great Things great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers can do. But we muſt not think of Pioniers for this Work; our Soldiers muſt do it themſelves. And they will do it chearfully, if thoſe that labour have ſome Pay extraordinary. Which was the way of the old Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Grandfather and great Uncle of our King. Moreover the place where we Intrench, will be the place we intend for a Garriſon. And the Line which may be full mann'd by ten thouſand Men, when the Works are compleated; may contain the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for a time. For none of theſe Garriſons ſhould be leſs than ten thouſand: the greater they are, the farther they will command, and the better they will maintain themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30410:8"/>
            <p>And now I come to the point remaining, which is, That 'tis hardly poſſible that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould take theſe Garriſons from us. And this is evident of it ſelf; if the Places be (as they ought) relievable by Sea, and not commanded by Land. A Place that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly fortified; that hath a great Garriſon, with great ſtore of Cannon, and hath room for great Renforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and that lying oppoſite to <hi>England,</hi> with a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Sea between, may receive theſe Renforcements (and all manner of Supplies) with every Snatch of Wind; I ſay ſuch a Place as this, may juſtly be reputed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable.</p>
            <p>Thus I am come to the End of the Project: which is the Eſtabliſhing ſome Garriſons upon the Coaſt of <hi>France.</hi> There is no more to be done: the reſt will do it ſelf. And as I have ſaid elſewhere; England <hi>will then be glorious, when we have a Range of Garriſons the whole length of the Channel, upon</hi> French <hi>Ground, and maintain'd by</hi> French <hi>Contributions.</hi> Every ſuch Garriſon, with a thouſand or two of Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons put into it, would diſmember a whole Province. If <hi>Tourville,</hi> when he Landed ſo eaſily at <hi>Torbay,</hi> had had an Army on board him, and had ſettled a rampant Garriſon there, would not the whole County of <hi>Devon</hi> (and <hi>Cornwall</hi> to boot) have been diſmember'd by it? And had not <hi>Deal</hi> (or any place upon the <hi>Downs</hi>) done the ſame by <hi>Kent;</hi> and any place in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and another in <hi>Dorſet,</hi> diſmembred each of thoſe Counties? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the <hi>French</hi> were ſtill Maſters at Sea; and had ſtill an Army on board, to pour in upon us (when they pleas'd) from any of thoſe places, Conſider, what a horrible Condition we had then been in. and in the ſame Condition will <hi>France</hi> be, in caſe this Project be duely proſecuted. They will be ſo diſtracted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded by it, that they will never be able to reſiſt the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30410:9"/>Confederates, aſſailing them in all Quarters. We may then hope for a good and ſpeedy End of this Warre: whereas by keeping our Army in <hi>Flanders,</hi> there is no hopes of it. For as things go there, tho our Forces be never ſo great, tho we over-power the Enemy never ſo much, we muſt account it a Glorious Succeſs, if we take one Town in a year. But what doth this ſignify to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards making an end of the Warre? At this rate we may be twenty years in recovering <hi>Flanders:</hi> And we, for our parts, ſhall be ruin'd in the tenth part of that time. For if our Forrain Payments continue two years longer, they will entirely Ruin us: and I doubt one year will do it.</p>
            <p>If from <hi>Flanders</hi> we could carry the Warre into <hi>France,</hi> there would be ſome hopes. But 'tis plain we cannot do this, becauſe we do not. Tho 'tis a great wonder that we cannot. Why cannot We March into <hi>France,</hi> as well as the <hi>French</hi> have march'd ſo often into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> the <hi>Dauphin</hi> into <hi>Germany</hi> two years ago; and the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> to <hi>Vienna,</hi> a hundred Miles within the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Quarters? As for the <hi>French</hi> Lines, they are a meer Cuckow Hedge. We might not only fly over it, (as we did at <hi>Namur,</hi> to beſige that place), but might go beſide it: their Quarters beyond the <hi>Maes</hi> lying open But as I have ſaid elſewhere, <hi>The great and ſwift Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours in all Ages, never lay pelting at Frontier Garriſons, but broke into the Countries.</hi> We ſhall never ſee a good Concluſion of this Warre, till the Warre be carried into <hi>France:</hi> and ſince that cannot be done by Land, we muſt do it by Sea. which is the End and Drift of the Deſign here propoſed.</p>
            <div type="addendum">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30410:10"/>
               <head>Some looſe things are here added, relating to the Diſcourſe above-written.</head>
               <p n="1">1. No great number of Horſe are required for this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. For they are not uſeful either in Landing or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying: which are the things to be done. It ſeems there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſufficient, that a thouſand or two of them be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd at firſt, and about twice as many ly ready in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> till there be occaſion for them: that is, till ſome Garriſons be ſettled to which they may go. For to have them all on Ship-board while the Fleet and Army is upon Wing, and may be plying to and again for ſeveral days, would be too chargeable and cumberſome.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is no way neceſſary, that the Places we fortify ſhould be good Ports. The <hi>French</hi> have few ſuch upon this Coaſt: and for theſe Places, 'tis ſufficient if they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievable by Sea, and can receive and ſecure ſmall Veſſels. For the buſineſs of theſe Garriſons is; that we may har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs and torment the <hi>French,</hi> from theſe Garriſons. Perhaps another year, when the <hi>French</hi> are weaken'd and humbled, we may think of Attacquing their beſt Ports, and of a Voyage Royal. But at preſent we ſhould attempt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what we are ſure we can do: for what we are ſure we can do, will ſufficiently ruin the <hi>French</hi> King. It will coſt us ſome Labour, but we ſhall run no Hazard.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Voyage Royal, or a main Invaſion, will not be of that advantage, as the deſultory Sea Warre here propoſed. In that way we may perhaps do ſomething, if our Force be throughout ſuperiour, and We cleerly and for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance Maſters of the Field: But in the other way, we ſhall be ſure to do ſomething and to gain our point, tho the Enemies Force ſhould be much ſuperiour to Ours. By the firſt way, we ſhall only divide the Enemies Force by dividing our own, without any further Advantage.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:30410:11"/>
               <p n="4">4. Forty thouſand of our Men on Shipboard, will do more Service to <hi>Flanders</hi> by the Diverſion they make, then a much greater number kept there. And 'tis well known, how great benefit the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> received, by our Fleet with a few Land-Men aboard, hovering about <hi>Provence</hi> laſt Summer. It drew ſo many <hi>French</hi> to guard that Coaſt, that the Duke took <hi>Caſal</hi> the while without Interruption.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That brave-ſpirited Prince deſerves our higheſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards. And the Aſſiſtance we have given him may ſeem well beſtowed. But we cannot ſend more Money to <hi>Piemont,</hi> whence it will never return. It were better for us to expend twice or thrice as much in our own Seas: for That Money will return, or rather will never go from us. And this powerful Revulſive will be felt in <hi>Piemont,</hi> to its great Eaſe and Benefit. But let it be as it will, we muſt ſend away no more Money.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our Silver Coin thar is left, as Mr. <hi>Lowndes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes it, may be about five Millions and a half, (but ſome think, it cannot be neer ſo much): Whereof four Millions, being Clip'd half way, is in effect but two Millions. And ſo three Millions and a half is the Summe effective. What will become of us, if a full Moiety of this Money be carried to <hi>Piemont</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> this very next year; for the growing Expence, beſide great Debts that muſt be ſatisfied? And either the Payments muſt be there made by Money <hi>in ſpecie;</hi> or they muſt be made by Bills, with moſt grievous loſs, the Exchange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo high againſt us. So that 'twere better our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney went at once. And Merchants know that forrain Payments, whether made by Bills or <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> are the ſame thing in effect; and carry Money alike out of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="7">7. This height of the Exchange againſt us, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by our great Payments abroad, is an infinite diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30410:12"/>to our Merchants: and will continue as long as thoſe Payments do. to the ruin of our Trade, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of our Nation. As for our Clipp'd Money. That had no effect upon the Exchange, till <hi>Guineas</hi> did riſe: which was leſs than a year ſince. And when our Coin is reform'd, that Effect will ceaſe. But our forrain Payments are the more durable and ſubſtantial Cauſe. It is theſe Payments that make Silver more valuable, and better, and dearer, in other Parts than it is in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> We cannot have weight for weight: nor receive ſo many Ounces there, as we pay here. It is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that our Money never flies from us, but when Silver is more valuable in other places than in <hi>England.</hi> Now Silver (as all other Commodities) is there moſt valuable and deareſt, where it is moſt in demand. And 'tis moſt in demand, where there are greateſt Occaſions for it, and the moſt and greateſt Payments to be made. They therefore that are to make theſe Payments, muſt buy the Convenience of having Money there for that Uſe, and the Exchange will run high againſt them. Which is our preſent caſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I have omitted One Advantage, which we ſhall have in our Deſcents upon <hi>France:</hi> and that is, that we ſhall never want Men for this Service. Men will be as forward and willing to go for <hi>France,</hi> provided they have good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officers; as now they are backward and unwilling to go into <hi>Flanders.</hi> The Service in <hi>Flanders</hi> having got a very ill Name, amongſt our common Men.</p>
               <p n="9">9. I have alſo omitted one Leak of our Money, which is to be well conſider'd. We keep an Army in <hi>England,</hi> at a great Expence: and moſt of this Army are Forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Who living very cloſe, and ſpending little, lay up a good part of their Pay. It deſerves an Enquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be true that is ſaid of them; That they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30410:13"/>(even the common Soldiers, and much more the Officers) ſending their Money, which they thus ſave, to their own Countries. If it be ſo, tho the particular Summs be not very great; yet there being many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them, it may amount to a large Summ in the whole. And it may prove as bad to keep Forraigners in <hi>England</hi> as to maintain an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in Forrain Parts. Some think it no way neceſſary, to have a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Army in <hi>England.</hi> For the People of <hi>England</hi> are ſo firmly Knit to his Majeſty, both by Intereſt and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that there is little need of Forrainers to force us to Obedience. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is too ſevere, when he ſays in his <hi>Politicks,</hi> (<hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10.), That forrain Guards are Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical: for juſt and good Princes may have them. But ſome think that in <hi>England,</hi> under another King, forrain Guards and a forrain Army might be of dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful danger to our Liberties. Tho under his Majeſty now regnant, (who hath been our Redeemer, and is ſtill our Protector and Preſerver) there is no Cauſe to fear.</p>
               <p>I moſt humbly ſubmit theſe things, to the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our States now Aſſembled. 'Tis They that muſt take care, <hi>Nequid Reſpublica detrimenti capiat,</hi> That the Kingdom receive no prejudice: or rather, as things go now, That it be not deſtroyed. Which it muſt be, if we part with more Money; and which therefore we muſt not do. No Concerting of Meaſures, no Treaties or Agreements, can oblige us to Impoſſibilities; and that which cannot be done without deſtroying the Kingdom, is morally and honeſtly impoſſible. We may ſay ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and truly, that for us to part with more Money, is a thing that cannot poſſibly be done.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30410:14"/>
               <p>SInce the writing of the foregoing Treatiſe, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with great Prudence have Addreſs'd the King, that he will be pleaſed to procure; that the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Proviſions ſent from <hi>England</hi> to our Forces A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, may be exempted from Duties and Exciſes. Which is we may preſume, in order to the ſupplying our <hi>Flanders</hi> Army with thoſe Things from <hi>England,</hi> inſtead of ſending Money for that Uſe. And this, I confeſs, will put a great Stop to the carrying out our Money. But no ſmall Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Money muſt ſtill go to <hi>Flanders.</hi> For tho the common Soldiers may be content with Proviſions brought by Sea, yet the Officers will not. They muſt fare betten, and live like Gentlemen, and ſpend their Money. Which Money thus ſpent will amount to a large Summe. And what is ſpent in <hi>Flanders,</hi> is loſt to <hi>England.</hi> But in our Deſcents we ſhall ſpend no Money: and all muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what they have from <hi>England,</hi> or can get from the Euemy. Moreover, tho our ſupplying our <hi>Flanders</hi> Army from <hi>England</hi> may leſſen the Neceſſity of a Deſcent, yet the Convenience and Advantage of it continues the ſame. And we may be confident, the <hi>French</hi> dread it above all things in the World. According to all humane proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, it will in one Summer give the <hi>French</hi> Tyranny a mortal Wound, if not break it to pieces. Eſpecially if our whole <hi>Quota,</hi> our whole eighty ſeven thouſand Men, were employed upon it. And if but forty thouſand were thus employed, the reſt (if it muſt be ſo) being in <hi>Flanders</hi> and elſewhere, we might well expect great things.</p>
               <p>Some think that a Naval Army might do great things, without the help of Garriſons. But that is a miſtake. For they can do nothing, as to ravaging and commanding the Country, without Horſe; and theſe cannot readily disbark and reimbark. Beſide, by being long on Ship-board, the Horſes will be diſabled and ſpoil'd. And in this way, it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30410:15"/>will be thought a great Adventure, if we go five Miles from the Sea-ſide. But if we have nothing to do, but to croſs over to a Garriſon or ſtrong Quarter of our own, where we may Land without any poſſibility of Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and where a good Body of Horſe lyes ready to joyn us; we may make a much greater Impreſſion.</p>
               <p>In caſe we have only one Garriſon, the <hi>French</hi> may perhaps coop it up with Lines, after their <hi>Flanders</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. But in caſe we have ſeveral, back'd by our Naval Army, they can never bear up againſt them. So that tho they had no other Enemy, and ſhould oppoſe us with treble our Force; ye we ſhould be too hard for them, having ſo great an advantage. And this is the way to put a ſpeedy and victorious End to the Warre: without ſending out, or carrying out our Money. Whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; this heavy and deſtructive Warre is like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, our Money like to be all gone, and the Kingdom to be utterly ruin'd.</p>
               <p>And thus much hath been ſaid about Keeping our Money. The Mending I leave to Others. But the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Reſolves of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> have made that work ſhort and eaſy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
